<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A ryght notable sermon, made by Doctor Martyn Luther, vppon the twenteth chapter of Iohan, of absolution and the true vse of the keyes full of great co[m]forte. In the which also it is intreated of the mynysters of the Church, and of scolemaisters, what is dewe vnto them. Ande of the hardnes and softenes of the harte of manne.</title>
            <title>Predigt am Sonntage nach Ostern. English</title>
            <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16992</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108931</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844583</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844583</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9412</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06520)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9412)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 136:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A ryght notable sermon, made by Doctor Martyn Luther, vppon the twenteth chapter of Iohan, of absolution and the true vse of the keyes full of great co[m]forte. In the which also it is intreated of the mynysters of the Church, and of scolemaisters, what is dewe vnto them. Ande of the hardnes and softenes of the harte of manne.</title>
                  <title>Predigt am Sonntage nach Ostern. English</title>
                  <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
                  <author>Argentine, Richard, d. 1568.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p. : ill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Anthony Scoloker. Dwellyng in. S. Nycholas paryshe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Ippeswich :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1548.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Predigt am Sonntage nach Ostern.</note>
                  <note>Translated by Richard Argentine, whose name appears on a2r.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title: Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Absolution --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9412:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9412:1"/>
            <p>A ryght no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſermon / made by Doctor Martyn Luther / vppon the twenteth Chapter of Iohan / of abſolution and the true vſe of the keyes
/ full of great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. In the which alſo it is intreated of the mynyſters of the Church / and of Scole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſters / what is dewe vnto them. Ande of the hardnes and ſofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the harte of manne.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>¶ Iohan. xx. ¶</bibl>
               <p>Whoſe ſynnes ſoeuer ye remitte / they are remytted vnto them
/ and whoſe ſynnes ſoeuer ye retayne / they are retayned.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRINTED</hi> at Ippeſwich by Anthony Scoloker. Dwellyng in. S. Nycholas Parryſhe. Anno. 1548.</p>
            <p>¶ Cum Priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:9412:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the biblical verse, John
20.23</figDesc>
                  <head>
                     <q>Whoſe ſinnes ſoeuer ye remytte they are remitted vnto them / ande whoſe ſynnes ſoever ye retayne / they are retained.</q>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9412:2"/>
            <head>¶ Vnto the ryghte honorable and his mooſte ſynguler good lorde / my lorde wentworthe. Rychard Argentyne wyſſheth increaſe of honour peace and proſperous ſucces / in all his procedinges.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit (ryght honorable) that the prophecye of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob was true / that the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pture was not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye from Iuda / vnto the tyme that Silo came / the very true Meſſias / both God and man. Yet dyd the almygtye GOD puniſh the Iewes wyth blyndnes / chefelye / for their Hipocriſye and Idolatrye / ande ſpoyled them of the mooſt holy a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d right gouuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce. Where therfore it myght appere / that Antechriſt was mooſt iuſtlie a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye extirped all together with his vſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped power oute of this mooſte fortunate realme and yet the ſame remained in dede ſtill i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of god / with his abhomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder the cloke of i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>numerable ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge gods / which by his perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s were dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ith pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, teples golde / ſiluer / pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyous<pb facs="tcp:9412:3"/>ſtones and other coſtlie thinges / to ſtyrre there by the people / both to be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes vnto them / and to honour them / wherby (Chriſt beyng clene exti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guiſſhed) myſerably we haue iuſtifyed the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye of the Iewes / that of iuſt cauſe the Turke (as the ſcourge of God) doth ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore hate and perſecute Chriſten men.</p>
            <p>It hath pleaſed almightie god of his gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at mercy / to ſend vnto vs a Ioſias / and a Kynge of mooſt worthye fame / clene to weede oute the ſame / commaundyng god and his holye woorde frelie to be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all his louinge ſubiectes / and Chriſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelie truelie ande ſyncerelye to be taught ande redde euery where / the which is the very true keye / wherby to enter into the Kingdome of heauen / ande the nexte wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye / to obteyne the mightie ande ſtronge ſwearde / for euer to beate downe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and hys derelie beloued antechriſte. For thoſe trulie / did not receyue / with the Apoſtles / at the handes of the holighooſt / the auctoritie of the keies of heauen / that teache theyr owne tradicions / ande not Chryſt onelye / and the infinite mercy of God / And yet ſo moche hath been the cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the fayned vertues of the aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named ennemy of God. Hys painted ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes<pb facs="tcp:9412:3"/>haue bene ſo moche exalted / his colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red lyghtning / is ſo moche dredde in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Realmes (the more pitie) euen at this daye / that there by he maketh him ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe not onelie the vicare of god vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth / but alſo a ſhamefull myxed thynge / ſet a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d boaſted vnto the woorlde / as a certeyne God of the earth / being both dradde ande honoured euen aboue God him ſelfe / and is in dede but a man of ſinne / and the ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. To the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t therfore / that thauctorite of his keyes / maye the better be knowen / I haue tranſlated a ſermon / declaring the true vſe of the keyes of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution / whome the biſſhoppe of Rome hath ſhamefully abuſed. Geuinge that for a token of my harte / vnto your good lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſhippe / that other by you (yf your plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure ſo ſhalbe) maie haue the fruytion of ſo great a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte / to the maintenaunce of holie learninge. That the intereſt of his deceptfull iugglinge maye vtterly be bannyſhed for euer. Ande thus Ieſu pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue your lordeſhippes eſtate vnto gods honoure. Fare you well.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>¶ At Ippeſwyche
<date>the 20 daye of Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry / the yeare of oure lorde.
1.5.48.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9412:4"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the biblical verses, John
20.21-23</figDesc>
                  <head>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>¶ Iohan. xx. ¶</bibl>
                        <p>Peace be wyth you. Lyke as my father ſent me / euen ſo ſende I you. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had ſaide that / he breathed vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſayde vnto them. Receaue the holy ghooſt / whoſe ſynnes ſoeuer ye remytte they are remitted vnto them and whoſe ſynnes ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ye retayne / they are retayned.</p>
                     </q>
                  </head>
                  <p>Recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve the holy gh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. Goſpell.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9412:4"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE lorde teacheth by the wordes of thys Goſpell / what proffyt he hath done vnto vs / by his reſurrex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion / that is to vnder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / that by that he hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and inſtituted a kyngdome / in the which it is intreaced / not of golde or ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer / nor of other thinges that are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye to paſſe ouer this oure lyfe / or by what craft or wayes thoſe thynges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye be inuented / or by what reaſon / ſoche beinge gotten maye be preſerued. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye this Kyngdome whych doth conſiſt in theſe earthely ande corporall thynges / was inſtitute nowe before ſtrayghtwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes in the beginninge of the worlde / ande being fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that time eſtabliſſhed / it taketh force and endureth / ande is ſubiect by the worde of God vnto mannes reaſon ande prudence / Geneſis the fyrſt chapter / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re God ſaith thus.<note place="margin">Gene. 1. The ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> Be ye lordes vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fyſſhes of the ſea / and the birdes of the ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vppon all thinges hauing life that moueth vppon the earth. etc.</p>
            <p>This is the olde kingdom in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof / the ſeculer magiſtrate is occupied / neither is there any nede of the
<pb facs="tcp:9412:5"/>holighooſt for the myniſtration of this kyngdome / neither do the holy ſcriptures chefely intreate of this / to teache by what reaſonnes that maye be gouuerned.</p>
            <p>But it apperteineth vnto the office of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as are learned in the lawe / to teach and counſell what is the reaſon of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of this kingdome.</p>
            <p>But beſydes this earthely kingdome / ther is alſo an other / that is to ſaye / the kyngdome of conſciences / and a ſpirituall kyngdome
/ the which doth gouuerne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyences / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the which it is intreated of theſe buſyneſſes that are betwixt vs ande God.<note place="margin">The ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is of ijſortes.</note> Trulye thys Kyngdome is of two ſortes. The one was inſtituted by Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes / the other is erected and inſtituted he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re by Chriſte. Where he ſaith. Lyke as my father hath ſent me / ſo do I ſend you etc.</p>
            <p>The vſe of Moſes kingdome is this / to teach vs what ſynne is / and which are trulie good woorks and which are euell. Into this kyngdome muſt thoſe be ſent / which truly as yet do not knowe theyr ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / nor feale them. Of the whych ſorte thoſe are / which are agaynſt the lawe
/ the which do teach that the lawe is not to be preached. Thoſe that are ſoch as fele not the hardnes of the lawe of Moſes / ande<pb facs="tcp:9412:5"/>the wayght of the ſame / they can not eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me as it is worthy / the grace of the goſpel / or the benefite of Chriſt / or with glad har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to embrace the ſame / or to deſire it from the botome of their harte. Wherfore thou ſhalt in vaine teach amonge thoſe moche of the grace that is gotten by Chriſt / for where the lawe is not taught / ande well beaten into them / there do me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knowe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of ſynne / what thing it is / howe great the crudelitie and abhomination of it is / and which are the true ande mooſte greuous ſinnes / as. S. Paule doth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe / ſayinge.
<note place="margin">Wherfore the lawe was geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Without lawe
/ ſynne is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad. Alſo where the lawe is not / there is no tranſgreſſion. For howe great a thynge ſynne is / and alſo / howe great the wrath of God is againſt ſynne / it can not be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen but by the lawe. Wherfore / where the lawe is not pricked forth / nor dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and inſtauntly beaten in to them / there plainely men are Ethnikes and Propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne parſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / thinking the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to do well / yea / and excellently to do the thing / whan they do abhominably ſynne agaynſt the preceptes of God.</p>
            <p>The wordly power doth reſtrayne a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d puniſh / thoſe manyfeſt and groſſe miſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous actes ande ſynnes / but what ſynne
<pb facs="tcp:9412:6"/>is before God / it can neither declare nor teach / although ſhe ſhuld take to counſell all the heapes of the bookes parteininge to the lawe. Therfore was the lawe geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs / that we therby myght learne to knowe what ſynne is / for where ſynne is not knowen there is no remyſſion / ande grace can not be vnderſtand / moche leſſe deſyred and coueted / and more ouer than is there no vſe of grace / for grace ought to fyght againſte ſinne and to vanquiſh it in vs that we deſpayre not.</p>
            <p>Wherfore lyke as it is neceſſarie for a phyſician (that wyll with praiſe profeſſe his arte / and be like vnto his name a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge) to haue the vſe of longe experience / and to be exerciſed moch a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d longe time in that ſcience that he maie knowe and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che oute / fyrſt what / and what kynde of deſeaſe it is and alſo what are the cauſes therof. For if he ſhall endeuoure to reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die the ſicknes (the dyſeaſe not beyng kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen / nor the cauſes of the ſame fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te) he ſhall rather gyue a poyſon / then the remedie or helpe of the ſame. Euen ſo is it neceſſarie fyrſt ſynne to be knowen before that grace be preached. And for the know leadge of ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne / the lawe is nedefull. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fyrſt inſtruction of a chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:9412:6"/>is diligently to be taught / ande the tenne commaundementes are to be interpreted well / and beaten into the people and that is neceſſarie to be done in ſermons in the temples. For reaſon (as I haue ſaide) is a great deale to weake / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to full of imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitie / with all her wyſdome / ande wyth all
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>awes and preceptes of all the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> men of the lawe / to parfourme that. And albeit that we graunt / that chefelie in reaſon is p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced and graffed a certeine knowleadge of the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge chat is honeſt a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d diſhoneſt / yet is that ſo ſmall and thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e / that it can not ſufficiently knowe the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d noughtines of her nature and the greatnes of ſinne. And therfore god hath inſtituted by Moſes / this doctrine ande preachyng of the lawe / the which he had ceyued before of the fathers.</p>
            <p>The other kyngdome is that which the reſurrection of our lorde Ieſus chriſt hath made. For by his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de beginne ande erecte a newe kyngdome the which ſhuld reſiſte ſynne (when by the lawe they are knowen) death and hell / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d doth reſtrayne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / take them a waye and aboliſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / neither doth this ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teach vs howe matrimonies maie be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tracted / howe the prouiſyon of the houſe at home<pb facs="tcp:9412:7"/>and of the publike weale / ande Empyres are to be gouuerned ande miniſtred. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we peace ande concorde vppon the earth and the ſocieté of men is to be preſerued. Howe we muſte buylde / ſowe / plante / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d tyll our landes, etc. Of this (I ſaye) this other kyngdome teacheth nothing. But it is therfore erected / that we maye knowe where we muſt dwell / or whether we muſt go from hence / that we maye ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue perpetuallye / when this corruptible a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d bodely kingdome will fayle / and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion of thys life ſhall haue an ende / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oure goodes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d all our faculties / honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / promocions / houſes and landes / the woorlde and what ſo euer is in it / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth oute of the earth / ande fynallye the lyfe it ſelfe is to be forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And trulie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath hangeth ouer vs / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is to be loked for euery momente.</p>
            <p>Yf adam had not ſynned / than neyther death nor any other calamytie ſhulde ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue bene fearfull vnto vs / neyther ſhulde any daunger haue bene vnto vs / by any kynde of euell. But nowe / throughe ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / death is brought into the worlde / and vppon all mankinde. From the which no man is ſure / no not for one momente of tyme / for as moche as euery moment ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:9412:7"/>hangeth ouer ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But to what place wilt thou flie? Whether wilt thou turne the? What minde ſhalt thou be in than? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doeſt thou ſuppoſe to go / when pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent death ſhall take the from hence? For this contention and for this agony is the kyngdome of Chriſte bought / the which for that purpoſe was appointed to be an euerlaſting kinge / that he might be lorde of ſynne and of iuſtice / of death ande life. Wyth theſe / the kingdom of Chriſt hathe to do. Vppon theſe he ruleth. He hathe theſe in his hande.</p>
            <p>Thus the lorde meaneth (in this place where he ſaith. Take you the holighooſt / whoſe ſynnes ſo euer you ſhall remitte / they are retayned.) to delyuer men from ſynne / or to declare vnto them that thoſe that dwell in ſinne / are to be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally. Here truly it can not be ſayde that a woorldly kingdome is inſtituted of him (as the Pope doth glory wyth a loudelye of the keyes of power and right to lowſe and binde all thinges / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by that meanes / to make that ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. whyche is no ſynne / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alſo that Chriſt him ſelfe doth not binde or lowſe / and ſo playnely he hath made by that meanes a worldy kingdome) But Chriſte doth here clerely ynough teach<pb facs="tcp:9412:8"/>what hys keyes are?<note place="margin">The keyes of Chriſtes kyngdom / ande what they be.</note> that is to ſaye / not to faſten ande to lowſe agayne lawes / as the Pope / but to remytte or retayne ſynnes.</p>
            <p>The ſentence therfore / and the ſomme of the wordes of Chriſte is. In this ſhall my kingdome conſiſt / this ſhalbe the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of my kingdom. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſt that men maye knowe them ſelves to be ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners. And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie that buſines is geven in commiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my ſervaunt Moſes / that by his lawe / he maye bringe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne into the knowledge of ſinne / not becauſe I wolde binde them (for why? they were bounde before / ande miſerably chayned) neyther ſhall I nowe do firſt that men may ſinne or geve an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſinne / neither wil I have any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to do with ſinne (as the Pope doth by his lawe and by his keies of bindyng / ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge / there
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be ſynne where none is) but I ſhall have to doo wyth them that natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally are ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners / or have ſynned agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes of God / that is to ſay / ſoche as contemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e God ſoche as beleve not in God / ſoch as deſpiſe the woorde of God / ſoche as gyue not vnto God his due obedience et cetera.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſinnes that is to ſaye the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of God / crudelite / blaſphemie / in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience and other lyke / are not made by<pb facs="tcp:9412:8"/>the law of the Pope / but are very ſinnes / cleauing and faſted in fleſh and bloude / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d borne even wyth man / the which can not be abſolued a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awaie by the Pope / by the keye (as he calleth it) of remiſſyon a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d abſolucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / after the ſorte as he vſeth it / but they cleave ſtyll a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d remayne in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as he leadeth this life / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not depoſe or laie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a parte vtterly but with the life</p>
            <p>Wherfore that we maie eſcape fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe ſynnes / for the which eternall dampnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remained vnto vs / and be deliuered from the payne of everlaſtyng death.<note place="margin">Wath the kingdom of Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> For that is the kingdome of Chriſt appointed and erected / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d therfor every where he calleth that his kingdome / not an earthely king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or worldly or pollytike / but the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen becauſe even than it ſhall take the begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this earthely ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom through death ſhall ceaſe to be / that men may knowe howe after this life / lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thys earthely kyngdome / they maye come into the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gdome. Of thys my ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gdom (ſayth he) thys ſhalbe the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner / after this ſort ſhal this my ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gdom be erected / ſtabliſſhed / delated a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d gouuerned.</p>
            <q>As my Father hath ſent me / ſo do I alſo ſende you et cetera.</q>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9412:9"/>That is to ſaie.<note place="margin">The office of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</note> You Apoſtles a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d your ſucceſſours vntill the worldes ende ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be my meſſangers or Ambaſſadours / by whome I haue purpoſed to reigne in all the worlde / ſo that you muſt take vppon you the ſame office the which I haue do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / vnto the which alſo I was ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te. That is to ſaie / that thoſe maye be deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne and death / whiche do feale their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d death / and deſire to be deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. Ande contrary / that ſoche as deſire not the helpe wherby they maie be redea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from them / but do put it awaie / that thoſe beying bound in ſinnes to death a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d detained / may ſo remaine. This ſhalbe your kingdome
/ this ſhalbe your miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie or ſeruice / ande this ſhalbe your office that you ſhall take vppon you.</p>
            <p>Vnto this kingdome it behoueth all ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che to ſubmitte them ſelues that are preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed downe and vexed with ſinne / yf they wilbe deliuered and lifted vp from them / and be partakers of the euerlaſting lyfe. Vnto thoſe that lygh vnder the heauy waight of theyr ſynnes / lygh groning
/ a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d are miſerablie troubled / Chriſte biddeth vs to ſaye / that they ſhulde be of good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not deſpayre becauſe of theyr ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
/ but lett them knowe that Chryſt by<pb facs="tcp:9412:9"/>his death and reſurrectyon
/ hath brought fourth vnto vs / the remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all ſinnes. Yf they heare this ande beleve it / they are ſaintes and they are ſaved. For yf their ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes be remitted / than hath death no ryght vppon them. But theſe that feale not nor knowe theyr ſynnes / nor are feared wyth the feare of death / ande do not penaunce / but procede conſtauntely / geving them ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues vnto bodely luſtes / as the pleaſure of the fleſh requireth / and liui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g after the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the olde man / Vnto theſe we ſaye by the commaundement of Chryſt / you ſhall remaine in ſinne / in indignation ande eternall death. For you aſke no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes and mercy / ande you do frowardely put from you and treade vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der fote everlaſtyng lyfe.</p>
            <p>Who (I praye the) can expreſſe with wordes howe infinite / howe ſubſtanciall ande full of health this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte is / that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne maie ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto an other with one wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the kingdom of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and cloſe vp the gates of hell? For as moche as in this ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom of grace (the which Chryſte hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) we do no other thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that we ſpeake with ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mouth. I remitte vnto the thy ſynnes / not of my ſelf / or by my propre power or vertue / but<pb facs="tcp:9412:10"/>in the name and ſteade of Ieſus Chriſt. For why? he ſaith not that you ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte ſynnes in your name (for no man liuing can remytte or retaine ſynnes) but he ſaith thus. Like as my father hath ſent me euen ſo I ſende you. I haue not done this by my counſell or arbitrement / but for this I was ſent from my father. And this commaundement I giue alſo vnto you / that you do the ſame vntyll the ende of this worlde / that you and all the world maie knowe this remiſſion or retaining of ſynne / not to be done by the vertue or power of man / but by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of him that hath ſent you.</p>
            <p>This is not onely ſpoken of thoſe that are miniſters and preachers of the woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of God / but of all faythfull Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Here maye euery vertuous man / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte and abſoile his neighboure in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonie of death / ande other neceſſities ande temptacions. When thou heareſt of me thys woorde / then doeſt thou heare that god will haue mercy on the / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d deliuer the fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſynne / iuſtifie the a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſaue the.</p>
            <p>But thou ſayeſt. I haue in dede harde the abſolution of the
/ but who knoweth / whether it be certaine that my ſynnes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo are forgeuen before God? I anſwere. Yf I had ſaid and done that / as man or of
<pb facs="tcp:9412:10"/>mine owne or of any other ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoryte alonely / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo to ſaye a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / thou mighteſt not without cauſe / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geuen / ſhuld be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter effectuall and auailable before God or no. And verely I haue hearde many / eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the extreme agony of death / doubti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of this thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / ſayinge / Oh woulde to god I knewe certai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly that my ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes are forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto me. I wold buy the certitude therof with all my poſſiblities and goodes. For albeit he be aparau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly neuer ſo good a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne that pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth the abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning his oune parſon
/ neuer ſo true / yet he that is grudged in conſcience a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the minde that is careful / is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with him / yea if thou thinkeſt hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
/ and ſeeſt in hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g elles than ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / than muſt thou nedes doubte a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d canſt nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſticke or truſt vnto his abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / nor any thing confyrme or erecte thy mynde by it.</p>
            <p>But if thou be certaine / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſte ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then thy mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt this doubte / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is it neceſſary that thy mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de (bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g taught a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtituted by the worde of God) ſaye after this ſorte. Neither the miniſter of the worde / nor yet any manne abſolueth me from my ſynnes / neyther hath my cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te taught me ſo to beleue / but god (by this miniſter or faithfull Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſhewwi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or<pb facs="tcp:9412:11"/>declari<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the remiſſion of ſinnes) hath do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne it. This is more certeine tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that / that is aſſured / for why? my lorde Chryſt hath commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the ſame / where he ſayd. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke as my Father hath ſent me / ſo do I ſende you et cet. Here doth he make equall and matche thoſe whome he ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth / vnto him ſelfe / in every thinge / as moche as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth theyr Ambaſſage or meſſage / that they (being ſente of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) maie do a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pedicyon perfourme that thynge for the which he was ſent from his Father / that they maye both remitte a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d retaine ſinnes. This is the thing that maketh that abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to be effectuall. Vithout this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement / Abſolution ſhulde be fruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate and vayne.</p>
            <p>Yf therfore thou (being laden with the burden of ſinnes) arte vexed and troubled in mynd. Yf thou quake for fear of death / by whome God ſhal puniſh ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes everlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d if thou (bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge in thys pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyuenes) doeſt heare of the minyſter of the church / the curate of thy ſoule a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thy biſhop / or els (where neceſſité co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelleth / that thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt not have the miniſter of the Churche) of thy neighbour that proffeſſeth chriſt a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte the / thou heareſt theſe or ſuche like wordes / Dere beloued brother<pb facs="tcp:9412:11"/>or ſiſter i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt / I ſee you careful a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d / ready to fall i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / to fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar the wrath a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God / becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of the ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes that thou perceiueſt / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for the which nowe thou arte ſo moche vexed a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d troubled / but heare a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſtrayght waies co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue in mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to the botom of thy harte that I ſhall nowe ſay vnto the. Ther is no cauſe why thou ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt deſpaire / be of good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort. For chriſt thy lord a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſauiour / the whych for ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners came i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to the world / that he might ſave the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hathe geve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / both vnto the miniſters of the church (which for the pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blick miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe called for that pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe) a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alſo (where neceſſité compelleth) vnto every priuate faithful chriſtian / that by his wordes / every ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort his neybor / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his name abſoil hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes.</p>
            <p>When thou heareſt this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte / ſee that thou receiue it with ſo great ioy of minde / wyth ſo moch gladnes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d kindnes / as th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough thou hardeſt it of Chriſt hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf.<note place="margin">Chriſt doth commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſinnes to be remitted and alſo to be retained.</note> So trulie he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded / ſaying / As my Father hath ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me / ſo do I ſende you / Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo / vnto who ſoever you remitt etc. That is to ſaye / ye ſhall take vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you the ſame office that I do. You ſhall execute the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me myniſtratyon that I do. If therfore<pb facs="tcp:9412:12"/>thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyve theſe wordes of Chryſt / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is thy harte pacified / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyueth a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial or ſure comforte / and than maiſte thou ſaye wythe a mery harte. I haue he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arde a man that hath talked with me / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted me. In as moche as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his owne propre parſon / I wold not credite the leaſt word of his ſaying / but I beleue my lorde Chryſt the which hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted this ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gdom of grace a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſynnes / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this power a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / that in his name they ſhuld remytt a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d retain ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Wherfor / when any <abbr>vtuous</abbr> man is aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaulted by the deuell and with the ſuggeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Sathan / that he is a great ſinner a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d therfor loſt a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned / than ought he not to deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to the place of fight with Sathan / nor to reaſon or to loue to be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary / or to hide hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf in ſom ſecrete place without arbytrement
/ but let hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome myniſter of the church / with who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me he is accuſtomed to cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes apperteini<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vnto his ſoules health / or lett hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſend for hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / or call hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him. Or if peraduenture no miniſter of the church be preſent / let hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> call vnto him / or let hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorte vnto his fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / whome he hathe kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be a louer of the worde of God and<pb facs="tcp:9412:12"/>vertuous / and let him complaine vnto hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſinnes / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of what ſoeuer difficulté doth oppreſſe him / and let him poure into his boſome / all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs wher with he is tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and troubled in mynde / requyri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g him of his counſell / and let him truſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the wordes of Chriſt. Vnto who ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you ſhall remytte theyr ſynnes etc. And where two or thre ſhalbe gathered to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether in my name / I ſhalbe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the middeſt of them. Truſting vppon theſe wordes / let hym aſſuredly beleue theſe things that the ſame brother or myniſter of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che or yf he be a vertuous fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / ſhall ſaie i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of the Lorde / oute of the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he ſhall beleue / ſo ſhalbe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto him. Yf he geue credyt vnto the abſolution / by the which he hath abſoyled hym in the name of Chryſt / then is he ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoiled / and hath remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes. etc.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What it is two or thre to be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the name of Chryſte.</note>Than trulye are two or three gathered to gether in the name of chriſt / whan they entreate amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt them ſelues
/ not of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ande earthely buſynes / howe they may haue great gaines / howe thy may ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther together great riches / by what wais a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that may be done / or of other cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall thyngs / of the whych this te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall lyfe hath nede / but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treate amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<pb facs="tcp:9412:13"/>them ſelues of thoſe things which do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteine vnto the edifying ande health of the congregation / that when in confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or elles where thou doeſt open thy vyces and temptacions / and whan he with who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me thou doeſt vnlade the ſecretes of thy mynde and thy cares / doth vnderſtand a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſe the to be feared and ſtonied with the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of Moſes / by thy ſynnes to be bitten / oppreſſed a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vexed and greuouſlye trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with the feare of death. And when with ſyghes and vnfained ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes thou doeſt lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and abhorre thy life / with theſe a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſoch like wordes / which procede from thoſe that are afearde in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. O wold to God I had not bene borne. Alſo / O wold god / wold prolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge my life / I wolde paſſe it ouer farre other wiſe and more holely / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue don hitherto. Li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke as that ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t doth in the goſpel / that did owe vnto his lord x. m. tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſayi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. Lord or maiſter / be patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t towordes me / and I ſhall reſtore vnto the all thinges.</p>
            <p>Whan therfore the miniſter of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che / or who ſoeuer elles ſhalbe / begynne to comforte the / not after a wordly ſorte / nor for the deſyre of lucre / (as the Pope doth / who ſayth / that he hath power ande faculté to lowſe and binde / but at no tyme but when thou ſhalt nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre vnto him / and<pb facs="tcp:9412:13"/>will redeme his bulles / pardons and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences / ) but becauſe he ſeeth thy care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and to be oute of all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte / through the feares of ſinne and death. And therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſaith vnto the. Forſake and deſpiſe all / thinges that are vppon earth / as money / riches / all mennes doinges / and the life. Loke not vnto thoſe thinges / turne thine eyes / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d all thy ſences from them / but gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue eare vnto theſe thinges that I nowe ſaye / faſten thoſe in thy minde. Thy harte is vexed
/ and thou deſireſt nothing more than to be deliuered oute of ſorrowes and care / ande thy conſcience to be cleared / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to eſcape thoſe ſharpe hornes of Moſes that ſtryketh ſo ſore. Here I ſaye / heare what thy brother ſaith / whome thou ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt to thy counſell / when he ſpeaketh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the / this ſentence. In the name of our lorde Chriſt / who ſuffred death for the. I declare and ſaie vnto the / that thou be of good comforte / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d beleue / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d be of a good and quiet minde / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d doubte nothing / that thy ſynnes are forgeuen vnto the / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that death hath no ryght vppon the.</p>
            <p>But thou ſayeſt. Howe wilt thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vnto me that it is ſo in dede? I anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / Chryſt oure lorde ſaide vnto his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and vnto all the catholike congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<pb facs="tcp:9412:14"/>I commaund and bidde that youre mytte ſynnes / or retayne them / If you ſhall do any ſoche thynge / you do it not of your ſelues / but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye do the ſame by my byddyng and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement / I my ſelfe do yt. For truly / the miniſter of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che that is to ſaye / the curate of thy ſoule and Byſſhoppe / or any other who ſoeuer he be (ſo that he be vertuous) in this neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſité / is called ande ſent therfore vnto the / to comforte the. Therfore thou muſt as moche beleue him (ſeyng he ſeketh onely the health of thy ſoule) as though Chryſt hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe beyng preſent / ſhuld ſtande by the / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d laying his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des on the / ſhulde abſoile the from ſynne. So truly he ſaith. I do ſende you that is to ſaye. I do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d geue vnto you full power a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / to do that thing / for which I was ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my father / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that I dyd. Wherfor yf any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> layi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
/ doth by this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſt declare vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the / thy remiſſion of ſynnes / it is as mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che as though Chriſt hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe had done it / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (I ſaye) he ſhall do it by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſt. For yf that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſt were not / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſhuld be do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne leſſe. And the mooſt mercifull lord for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that I or any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld be bold to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:9412:14"/>any ſoch thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g without his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
            <p>Beholde / this is the forme ande ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to remitte a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d abſoile ſinnes. That thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge can be done by no other reaſon / nor by any other meanes / no other cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell / no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther helpe is any where in any thing. For that doctrine of the Pope / is both erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d blaſphemous by the which me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do profeſſe / that by their works a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d propre me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rites they can obteine remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d therfore doth it bind me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſatiſfac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / to take vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſolitary life
/ or to make a pilgrimage vnto. S. Iames / or to builde te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples / or to edifie great Cathedrall churches and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries to ſinge Maſſes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to buy Par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dons and ſoche like. Theſe be not the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes or meanes / wherby the remyſſyon of ſynne maye happen vnto the. Theſe thy pilgrimages a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d theſe thy workes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des thou maiſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerte i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter vſe. In this buſines (as moche as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteineth vnto the meanes of health) they ſhall proffit the nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at all. For he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re it commeth to paſſe as it is ſaid / when muſes taketh vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym his hornes ande doth ſtrike the
/ that is to witte / when by the lawe / he doth declare vnto the thy ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the greatnes and multitude of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ande ſo doth caſt the into quaking feares<pb facs="tcp:9412:15"/>and deſperation. Than arte thou no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in that greate nombre of men that are full of ſecurité / and haue forgotten to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe / and can not repent / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d are obdura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / but in that litle nombre of theſe that do acknowledge theyr miſerie and ſinnes / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d do fele them
/ a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d therfore they wepe / wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le and tremble at the ruſſhyng af a leafe / and at the ſhadowe of a rede that is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Vnto thoſe a helpe is prepared. Vnto thoſe Chriſt ſaith I / I ſaye / haue inſtituted and eſtablyſſhed that kingdom of grace / which ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume / aboliſh ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vp and deſtroye ſynnes and death / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhall bringe vnto the iuſtice / and lyfe.</p>
            <p>Saye not therfore. Where ſhall I fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de it? where ſhall I ſeke it? Muſte I take any Iornate towardes Roome or towar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des Ieruſalem? Not ſo. For if thou ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt aſcend into heauen with golden lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders / if it might be brought to paſſe / yet ſhuldeſt thou not obteyne that thinge / by this meanes / that thou deſireſt. But this thou muſt do. Beholde a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d faſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thy min<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de theſe wordes ande co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of Chriſt. Who ſayth / I ſende you etc. As who ſhulde ſaye. It was nedefull that I ſhulde come fyrſt vnto you / that I ſhuld declare vnto you by the Goſpell or glad<pb facs="tcp:9412:15"/>tidinges / the will of my father / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that I ſhuld inſtitute ſacramentes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / or elles you could not haue come vnto me. Truly becauſe / I can not be corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in all places of the woorlde vnder a viſyble forme / neyther ſhall I be alwaies preſent in this propre parſon / therfore do I that that my father hath done. He hath ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me into this litle a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gle of the worlde / i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to Iury / that I ſhuld teach in it. But what taught he? He taught the glad tidi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte of miſerable ſynners / that we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in Iury / he healed the ſycke and dyd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſcitate the dead. This was the worke and miniſterie geuen vnto hym in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement. For this was he ſent from his father. There a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to this was he who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly geuen. In thoſe places was he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt / and dyd his offyce with faythfull intent and ſedulité / not in the Courtes of noble men / amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt glotons / ſmelkitche<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s theſe raueners more lyke ſwyne than me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / not with Annas and Caiphas and other Iuſticers / ryche a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d wiſe before the world / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſoche like me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne / but amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the bli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / the lame / the diſmembred / the halting / the lepers / the deafe / the dead a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the myſerable ſhepe that were wretchedly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and ſtrayinge abroade. With thoſe<pb facs="tcp:9412:16"/>was he preſent / thoſe dyd he make of / the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe did he helpe / curyng them both in body and ſoule / bringing vnto them the mooſt precious ande ineſtimable treaſure of the worlde / which no creature hath (moche more can it not geue it) excepte it receaue it from him / that is to ſaye / Iuſtyce ande euerlaſting health.</p>
            <p>Thus ſayth he here / You ſhall alſo. do it in all places wher as you ſhall come And for that ſame cauſe I ſende you / that you runne and be my Apoſtles ande meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſangers through all the worlde. And vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this office you ſhall ordaine a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te others alſo / the which maye teach ande do the ſelfe ſame thynge / vnto the whiche I was ſent from my father. And you are ſente by me / vntyll the worldes ende ande I ſhalbe alwayes preſent with you / that you maye knowe that you are not they that do that thynge / but I by you.</p>
            <p>By the force and ſtrengt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement / we alſo haue obteyned po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ande faculté / to comforte the ſadde and carefull conſcyences / ande to abſoyle them from ſynne. Ande we knowe when we execute this mynyſterye or exercyſe this acte / that we our ſelues do it not / but that Chryſt hym ſelfe doth it. Wherfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<pb facs="tcp:9412:16"/>euery vertuous man / in this caſe ande buſynes / muſt thynke / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he heareth his curate or the precher ſo in the pulpitt / that he heareth not man / but God hym ſelfe ſpeakinge / than maye he be certeyn / eande appointe in his mynde / that he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued full remyſſyon of all hys ſynnes / neyther is there left any ſticking or dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bte any more. For trulye Chriſte ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the ſo inſtituted by his reſurrection / that if any man that is laufully called the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Churche / or who ſoeuer fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in extreme neceſſyté doth abſoyle from ſynnes hys neyghbour that is aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed and doubtefull in mynde ande deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of comforte / the ſame is of ſo moche effect and value / as though GOD him ſelfe had done it / if truly it be done by his commaundement and in his name.</p>
            <p>Wherfore / when two after this ſorte intreate and talke betwyxt them ſelues / they are gathered to gether in the name of CHRISTE. For lyke as it is aboue ſayd vnto vs / none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both / he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re deſyreth or ſeketh for the goodes of the other / lyke as the Papiſtes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d gapers for advau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage do / which do not onely pol but alſo pill the Church / which do ſynge ande
<pb facs="tcp:9412:17"/>diſtill into the ſicke ſoche or like woordes / O man / the houre is now at hande that doth call the from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Remembre howe thow wylt diſpoſe thy goodes and thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties / that they maye be beſtowed into vertuous or Godly vſes.
<note place="margin">The auari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce or coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes.</note> See that thou forget not thy wretched ſoule / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſee that thou prouide for the helth of it. Gyue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs one parte of thy goodes / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d we ſhall praye for the / ande we ſhall do many good woorkes for the / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the merites of all our good woorkes / ſhalbe comune vnto the / with vs.<note place="margin">The ſayin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of a faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full myny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter vnto the ſycke.</note> This doth not he / which is god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in dede ſpeake vnto the ſicke / but vſeth theſe / or ſoch like wordes. O my fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the opportunité of the place a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d time / or the ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe of thy infirmeté doth not nowe ſuffer vs to haue many things to do of thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney ande of thy earthely goodes / let other men take cure of thoſe. I ſee thy harte to be troubled or ſtryken wyth the feare of death / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that thou arte in conflict with deſperatyon / and that thou haſte not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t helpe of thy ſelfe wherby thou mayeſt be able to rydde thy ſelfe oute of that dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger / and confirme thy minde againſt tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe fearfull thynges. But take a good harte vnto the / Chriſt hath inſtituted a ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gdom in earth full of conſolation and beatitude / <pb facs="tcp:9412:17"/>when he ſayde / like as my father hath ſent me ſo do I ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d you / with theſe wordes / he hath conſecrated vs all to be prieſtes / for this purpoſe / that one ſhuld declare vnto other the remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes. And therfore
/ I nowe come vnto the in the name of the ſame oure lorde Ieſu Chriſt / and I bidde the to be of good comforte. There is no cauſe why thou ſhuldeſt feare. There is nothing why thou ſholdeſt quake and be of a deſperate minde / as though ther we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re no ſolace / helpe or counſell any where. Doeſt thou not heare that Chriſt came not for the iuſt / but for ſinners to the pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe to ſaue them? Wherfore take a good harte vnto the
/ truſt aſſuredly / receue this glad tidinges wyth a glad minde / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with thy harte re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre vnto him tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes for this tidinges whiche he bringeth vnto the by me / without all labour / care ande charge of thy ſelfe. And beſydes this / alſo he hath geuen commaundement / that I ſhuld re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytre vnto the thy ſynnes / wherfore I forgeue all thy ſynnes vnto the / in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of the Father / the ſonne ande the holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghooſt. Wherfore / nowe with a glad mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / ſaye theſe wordes O mooſt mercifull God O heauenly Father I thanke th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> / that thou haſt forgeuen vnto me my ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / <pb facs="tcp:9412:18"/>by thy derely beloued ſonne Ieſus Chriſt nor doubte not / but of the lorde hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe the hauenly father thou arte abſoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of thy vniuerſall ſynnes.</p>
            <p>Of this thou ſeeſt / that theſe wordes of the office of the keyes doth i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no wiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyrme and eſtabliſh the tirannie of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. For chriſt did not therfore giue theſe ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ies. He did not therfore i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitute this mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie / that I ſhuld e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>riche the / or thou me / or that I ſhuld be lorde ouer the / or that thou ſhuldeſt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to be ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me / as the pope doth conuerte it into wordly power / magnyfycence and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion by the whiche acte he ſetteth forth a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d doth teſtifie / mooſt manyfeſtly / that he hym ſelf is a great Rybaulde / Antechriſt hym ſelfe / mooſt wicked / full of contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>te a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a deſpiſer of GOD / a blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and a mocker of CHRIST ande the traitour of his Churche. For Chriſte woulde not this / as I haue ſayde. He hath not by theſe wordes inſtituted any wordly Kyngdome and tyranny / but he had an eye to this purpoſe / this he wolde / and therfore he dyd inſtitute it / that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnto the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wraſtlyng with deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion / and gronyng vnder the harde bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den<pb facs="tcp:9412:18"/>of ſynnes (whether it be in the great agony of death / or any other tyme) I ſhuld ſaye vnto the (intending to lyfte the vp with comforte or counſell) let power / money / honoures dygnityes and ryches be remoued hens farre of / nowe may the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re not / neither ought any reſpect to be had of thoſe thinges. But nowe muſt we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twyxt vs entreate and talke of the Kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chryſte / by the which onely / and by none other thou canſt be delyuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne and death.</p>
            <p>This truly is not a forrayne ande a worldlye power and dominion / but it is an office and a miniſterie. For here truly I ſeke for nothing of the / I neither haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke nor wowe for any thinge wherby I maye be enryched / or to be lorde ouer the / and wherby I maye make the ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to make the my handſeruaunt / but I ſerue ande do exhibit the greateſt offyce that maye be vnto the. I brynge vnto the a great a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ineſtymable treaſure / not golde or ſyluer / but where as thy har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te that is oppreſſed wyth heauy care / doth covet to be comforted / delyuered ande confyrmed / ande to haue GOD mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto the in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfore come I
<pb facs="tcp:9412:19"/>vnto the bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging vnto the / the mooſt true Goſpell or tidings that is mooſt gladdeſt / mooſt pleaſaunt and mooſt to be deſyred / not of my ſelfe / not of my good intent / or of my propre cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell / but by the commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and meſſage of Chryſt. Who ſaith / Come you all vnto me / that labour a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d are lade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / I ſhall refreſh you. Alſo / Theſe thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche ye lowſe vppon earthe / ſhalbe lowſed in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / or els (as he ſayth here) Vnto whome you ſhall remitte their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are they forgeuen etc. Is not thys to ſerue? Is it not an office that is greateſt of all? and not to be compared withall for any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to do the better
/ when thankfully I bringe vnto the an ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble treaſure that is heauenly ande euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge? Whyche neyther thou / nor all the woorlde with all the goodes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d riches in it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neither match nor buy with money? For what are the vniuerſall treaſures of all the world / the Iewelles of all kinges
/ crownes / goodes / golde / precious ſtones / and what ſoever it maketh mooſt of / ande doth wonder at it / what are all thoſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in comparyſon of this treaſure / that is to ſay / the remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes / by the wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yche thou arte delyuered from the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye of the Devell
/ of death ande of hell.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9412:19"/>And arte certyfyed that God the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Father wilbe mercyfull vnto the / And ſo mercyfull / that for Chryſtes ſake / thou muſt be the ſonne and heyre of God / ande the brother and coheyre of Chryſte. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſoche ande ſo great a treaſure as this is / can not be bought or ſolde / or wayed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually with money / the which thynge the ſame our Iudas Iſcarioth the pope hath done. For excepte it be geuen ande taken thanckfully / and wyth mere grace / ther is no cauſe why that thou ſhuldeſt truſt to enioye the ſame thyng / or to take by it any commodyté. For the gyfte of God is not gotten with money.</p>
            <p>Truly I would not that any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld thynke that I haue ſpoken theſe thynges as though nothynge ought to be geuen or employed vppon the mynyſters of the ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urch which ſyncerely and trulye teach the worde of God
/ wherby they may nouriſh them ſelues / the which thinge at this daie certeyne parſons do gladlye in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / which do ſo envie their curates ande miniſters of their churches / that almooſt they numbre ande meaſure everye morſell of meate that commeth within theyr Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes / by all waies ande meanes that they can. They ſteale and pike vnto them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues
<pb facs="tcp:9412:20"/>thoſe eccleſiaſticall goodes / wyth the which the paſtours and myniſters of the worde of God ought to be nouriſſhed. And in ſo doying they declare ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly / that theyre ſtudie is to driue the miniſters of the worde vnto extreme pouerté ad dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of famyne / and ſo to dryue them from them / that there maye be none to teache / or to checke their vices. Truly what di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbaunce hereafter ſhall come. What deſolation of the Church. What myſerie. Nowe great a barbarouſnes ſhal there of follow we ſhall proue that / and that ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely / excepte the magiſtrates fynde ſome remedy for this myſchefe. In no caſe therfore do I ſpeake theſe thinges / nor yet ſo theſe thinges ought to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / as who ſhulde ſaye / that nothing ſhuld be geuen vnto the miniſters of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. For theſe thinges are dewe wnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherby they may nouriſh ande ſuſteyne commodiouſly and eaſely / them ſelues a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their familie. For except they haue wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth to lyue / wherwith to cladde them ſelue / where to dwell / and howe to defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de them ſelues / agaynſt the iniurie of col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ande heate / they can not longe do their office / but they ſhalbe compelled (forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge theyr offyce of teachynge) to ſeke<pb facs="tcp:9412:20"/>and finde howe to kepe them ſelues. The which thinge when it cometh to paſſe / the Goſpell can noth longe remaine. The which thing the deuell doth a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſeketh for the ſame purpoſe / that by this occaſyon he may take oure of the way and let the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A ſtypende is dewe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro the mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters of the Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch / 
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ordenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of God.</note> And that thinges are dewe vnto them / wherby they maie aptely nouriſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues / Chriſte doth teache that openly whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re he ſaith. The labourer is worthy of his reward. S. Paul alſo. He that is inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted / muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate vnto him that doth inſtructe him in all good thinges. And he dothe adde a terme / wherby iuſtly thoſe wicked parſons ought to be feared / the which is this. God is not mocked. Alſo. 1 Timoth. the. 5. Seniour or preſtes that are righte in auctorne / or that do gouuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne well / are worthy to be had in doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour ſpecially thoſe that by worde ande teaching do laboure. If that therfore ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendes be geuen vnto other that are pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike officers in thiges that they ſerue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a communalté / that by the ſame they maye with more expedition ſerue the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne wherunto they are called / moch more is it dewe vnto the miniſters of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / for trulie when we haue wyth all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence<pb facs="tcp:9412:21"/>and good will / geuen vnto them all thinges / wherby they may lyue commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly / yet muſt ye ſaye this. This ſtipend / this money or this grayne which we geue vnto the curate or miniſter of the worde / we geue it not for ſermons or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. (the which are not the propre thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of thoſe miniſters but of God / ande therfore they can not be ſolde of them for money) but for as moch as God hath ſo ordained / that we ſhuld heare ande recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the worde and his Sacramentes / of menne. Therfore is it neceſſarie that they be noriſſhed of the comun charge / or of the publike treaſure / or by our comune wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis. And we ſhall geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with glad mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / that they maie haue whervppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to liue / and that by that wayes they maie wyth better expedition do theyr office. The which thinge if it were not done / they ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be compelled to renounce their office / and ſo ſhulde we be ſpoiled of the doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Theſe thinges are mooſt true / and in dede of neceſſyté muſt be ſo done. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more if the doctryne of the GOS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PELL ought to be Preached purely ande to be ſect ouer or left vnto the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terytyté pure / We muſt prouyde not<pb facs="tcp:9412:21"/>onely for the miniſters of the worde a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious lyuyng / but we muſt beware a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d watche with all care ande ſtudy alſo / that the places appointed to teache in / or ſcoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of learning / maye haue apte Parſons / and that wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h oute difficulte the rulers of the ſcooles / 
<note place="margin">Stipendes muſt be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto Scoolemaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters</note> and the teachers of childeren may haue alſo meate and drincke and ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendes wherby they maye commodiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuſteine them ſelues / wherby thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye be brought vp / which in time to come maye be not onely comune preachers or onely apte for that purpoſe that they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye inſtructe with the word ſome one chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che / but ſoch alſo / that maye gett vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that doctryne and faculté that they maye be able not onely to teache in a pulpit / but alſo to contynue and reſiſte theſe that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ſecres and madde raging ſpirites / ande ſoch as are fooliſhſly inſenſed with falſe opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. For this vſe not onely the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and magiſtrates / but alſo the Cyteze<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and all the people of the countrey ought comunely to giue ſome parte of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties / that ſcoles might be preſerued / and that the church maye alwaies haue ſuch men / the which trulie ſhe can not lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / if the purité of the doctrine and the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alth of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation or churche ought<pb facs="tcp:9412:22"/>to be maynteyned.</p>
            <p>For of cheſe thinges that you haue he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arde / you maye eaſely gather / howe great and howe incomparable a treaſure ande not able to be eſtemed / is the puryté ande abſolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Goſpell / if it be hearde a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d receaued in a true ſence of a right and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full miniſter / when he commeth vnto the being ſicke / and dothe comforte the / thou oughteſt aſſuredly to perſuade thy ſelfe / and to beleue / that Chriſt the lord him fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe doth comme vnto the and comforte the. For no man wold euer ſo preſume to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſo vnto the / without the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God / neyther coulde any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe the with comforte or counſell / or gyue the any ayde. Nowe trvly / ſeing thou hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt that God hym ſelfe doth commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de it / thou maiſt without doubte / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with a glad mynde ſaye here chriſte him ſelf co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto me / in my confeſſour or cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. For he doth not ſpeake his owne but the worde of god / for the whych he is ſent and the which is geuen in commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto hym of God. This / whan a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath perſuaded with him ſelfe / that God hath ſent him / and hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded thoſe thinges to be declared / than doth the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re and the carefulneſſe of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe<pb facs="tcp:9412:22"/>and is quenched / than is the minde erected and pacefyed wich comforte / and beginneth to haue a good hope / neyther is there than any cauſe why to waver a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to be in doubte ande to be in a wane hope and to ſticke in doubte. The whych thing muſt nedes be in thoſe that followe the doctrine of the pope.<note place="margin">The Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.</note> For that doctrine taught that men ought to doubte / neither dyd that abſoyle anye man from ſynnes excepte he departed with ſufficient ande due iuſtice / and full contricion / ande had cofeſſed all his ſynnes. Here was no me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion made / not ſo moche as a worde of faith / ande of the vertue of the keyes that are inſtitute by Chriſte. Truly thys doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine ande knowledge was ſo obſcured ande vnknowen / ande playnely buried / that I my ſelfe / euen than whan I was made doctor / (which certeynly ought by no meanes to be rude or ignoraunt in this matter) dyd thinke no otherwyſe / nor taught otherwyſe / then that than fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally the ſynnes to be remitted vnto me and vnto other / if we had done / or had to a full a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d iuſte ſorte parfect or due contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion / ande were confeſſed. But of a tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth / if oure ſynnes ſhuld not be forgeuen <pb facs="tcp:9412:23"/>vnto vs / before that we with our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>triti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or compunction and wyth other good woorkes ſhulde waie downe the ſame / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d before that nothing might be required in them / than myght I neuer truſt for any remiſſion of ſinnes. For I can neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termyne with my ſelfe that I haue done full and iuſt contrycion / and therfore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordig vnto that / no man can abſoile / whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther he be Pope or any other what ſoever he be.</p>
            <p>So by the popyſh lyes the conſciences are miſerably ſeduced a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d called awaye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the woorde of faythe and the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God / vnto his vncerteyne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition and compunction of harte. And this theyr doctrine hath gotten by extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion infinite ſommes of money / and hath encreaſed them with great ample ryches and kyngdomes.<note place="margin">The occaſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of the po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyſh power</note> And by thys meanes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo / ſo manye Temples monaſteries great Churches / ande Cathedrall Churches / Chappelles and Aulters are builded and indued withe large or ample gyftes ande coſtes. And at thys daye theyr are bulles and Popyſhe pardones that are ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t witneſſes of theſe thynges / and doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme thoſe buyldinges ande gyftes / by the whyche the POPE hath wretche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye<pb facs="tcp:9412:23"/>deceiued all the woorlde / ande hathe by theſe faierynges / or buying and ſellig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done ſo moch harme vnto the Church of Chriſt / that no man can compryſe wyth mynde / nor expreſſe with wordes the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atnes of that calamité and iniurie.</p>
            <p>For that cauſe / we do often and dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exhorte. And let thoſe with vs with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall ſtudie do the ſame / that in this caſe doth helpe vs / as manie as maye / that ſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les / cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d miniſtries of the worlde / be earneſtly maintained / leaſt ſoche an other errour / or rather worſe (the which thing Sathan doth endeuour with the greateſt ſtudie that he can) crepe in againe.
<note place="margin">The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the Goſpell pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re.</note>If tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye we wyll preuent and withſtande this miſchefe / that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no otherwiſe be done bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter / than if the youth euen from theyr yon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ande tender age / be well ande vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly taught and brought vp / the whiche ſucceding after vs / when we are departed vnto Chriſt / maye not onely ſet forth and beate into the people diligently the pure doctrine / but alſo maie defend the ſame / againſt madde raging and erronious tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers / and put of wycked a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d falſe / opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s For trulye it is a great benefyt of God / when ſoch parſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are apoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted miniſters / the whiche do ſyncerely teach the worde<pb facs="tcp:9412:24"/>of GOD rightly and purely. And beſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des thoſe alſo / it is neceſſarie that ſome be that can preſerue learning / and defend the ſame / leaſt the Church be infected and cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupted with theyr poyſon and wicked er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.<note place="margin">The neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyte of ſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les.</note> For that purpoſe it is neceſſarye / that vniuerſities or ſcooles be mayntey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned / from whence ſoch men do at length come / the which may fyght or contend for the doctryne / ande preſerue the purité of the ſame.</p>
            <p>When truly we do employ to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe either our labour or faculties / that ſoch men maye be in the Church / that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye teache purely and that may alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te the ſorrowfull ande afflicted concienſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / according vnto the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſt (as we haue ſayde) and may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine and conuince the wolues and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked doctours. And when thoſe haue well prouided for them thynges neceſſary / and large and due ſtipendes / than that ought not to be adiudged as a ſufficient recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe / wagis or price / for thoſe benefites which happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but it muſt be thought that it is a thankfull ſacrifice / and a geuing of thankes and a due pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe vnto God.<note place="margin">Praiers muſt be ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de for the preachers of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che.</note> And alſo we muſt diligently praye / lyke as Chriſte doth admoniſh vs / <pb facs="tcp:9412:24"/>that he will vouchſafe to ſende ſoch wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke men into his harueſt. For why? tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers trulye ſhall alwayes be / but except he ſend them / they ſhall not be Godly / faithfull and pure.</p>
            <p>After this forme is it ryghtly taught and beleued of the Kyngdome of Chriſte / and of the power and miniſterie of the ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes. Ande if we directe our ſelues after this forme / than remayne we Chriſtians / and than maye we parforme the offyces or dueties that we owe both vnto God and man / and ſone dyſcharge oure ſelues from all kynde of doctrines ande opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons / and to iudge of them rightlye.</p>
            <p>And then alſo ſhall we giue GOD than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes from our harte / that he hath delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs from the tormentes / ſlaughter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe and tyranie of the Pope / who doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uert the power of the keyes into a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine clere ande infinite power / ande vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roare ande a worldly dominion / when notwithſtanding the power of the keyes was appointed and ordeyned of Chryſt / 
<note place="margin">The ende of the keies of Chriſt.</note>for this ende ande vſe onely that that trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure ſhuld be offered a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d exhibited vnto all the world / the which may be waied dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d bought with no ſommes of money<pb facs="tcp:9412:25"/>nor with no riches ſauing that we muſt teſtifie and declare our benignité piété or godlynes ande gratitude / with our bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fietes / liberalité of our faculties / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with our offices / towardes thoſe that do exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute this miniſterie / the which are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of double honoure... Timoth. 5.</p>
            <p>Let vs therfore geue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes vnto chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte our lord / that he hath by his reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion inſtitute ſoch a kingdome of grace / for this purpoſe / that we ſhuld haue ande finde in that in all our neceſſities a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles / alwayes a preſent help and a ſure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte / neither is this treaſure to be ſought for / oute of regio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s farre of / neither is ther moch labour or paynes to be ſpent for the ſame / neither are great coſtes to be done when we buy it vnto vs. For Chriſt hath geuen commaundement and full power vnto his Apoſtles / yea / in neceſſite vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery vertuous ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beleueth in Chriſt euen vntyll the worldes ende / that they maye erect a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme thoſe that are wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in faith and ready to fall into deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / wyth comforte. And in his name forgiue ſynnes. etc. Of the which thing let this be ſpoken ſuffyciently.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>A faute in the .ij leafe / iij. lyne the ſcrypture reade the ſcepter was not.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9412:25"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
